<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site.
 It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content.
 You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another.
 This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site.

 To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps:
 1. Log in to that site as an administrator.
 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel.
 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list.
 4. Activate & Run Importer.
 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page.
 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users
    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an
    existing user on the site or to create a new user.
 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc.
    contained in this file into your site.
-->
<!-- generator="WordPress.com" created="2020-12-27 02:20"-->
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <channel>
<title>Katy Dynarski</title>
<link>http://biogeokaty.com</link>
<description>ecosystem biogeochemist &amp; science writer</description>
<pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 02:20:37 +0000</pubDate>
<language>en</language>
<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
<wp:base_site_url>http://wordpress.com/</wp:base_site_url>
<wp:base_blog_url>http://biogeokaty.com</wp:base_blog_url>
<wp:author>
  <wp:author_login>katydynarski</wp:author_login>
  <wp:author_email>katy.dynarski@gmail.com</wp:author_email>
  <wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[katydynarski]]></wp:author_display_name>
  <wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[]]></wp:author_first_name>
  <wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[]]></wp:author_last_name>
</wp:author>
<wp:term>
  <wp:term_id>1357</wp:term_id>
  <wp:term_taxonomy>nav_menu</wp:term_taxonomy>
  <wp:term_slug>primary</wp:term_slug>
  <wp:term_name><![CDATA[Primary]]></wp:term_name>
</wp:term>
<wp:term>
  <wp:term_id>306141178</wp:term_id>
  <wp:term_taxonomy>nav_menu</wp:term_taxonomy>
  <wp:term_slug>social</wp:term_slug>
  <wp:term_name><![CDATA[Social]]></wp:term_name>
</wp:term>
<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/06/cropped-img_0952-002.jpg?w=32</url>
	<title>Katy Dynarski</title>
	<link>http://biogeokaty.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<item>
  <title>Green Mountains, Red Mountains, and White Mountains (oh my!)</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 19:49:50 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=382</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[The snowpack in the Sierra Nevada has been delightfully persistent this spring/summer, which is great for backcountry skiing but less great for my desire to go backpacking with my roommate. The rather excellent side effect is that I’ve taken multiple trips up to the Trinity Alps this year, where access to the high country has been relatively easier than in the Sierra. Nestled at the southern end of the Klamath Mountains, the Trinity Alps Wilderness is one of my favorite places in California, and I frankly don’t spend as much time up there as I ought to because of the four hour drive that’s involved with getting to nearly any trailhead. I am grateful for the intervention of the universe that has forced me to point my car north this year.

In my various perusals of hiking blogs, I’ve seen mentions of  the “Red Trinities” and the “White Trinities,” a distinction I have always assumed was made due to the different colors of rock. However, every time that I’d hiked in the Trinity Alps they just looked gray to me, so I wasn’t really sure what people were talking about. Some brief googling informed me that the Trinity Alps can roughly be divided into the Green Trinities in the west, named for their abundant timber, the Red Trinities in the east, named for the reddish rocks found in the edge of the mountain range, and the White Trinities in the heart of the wilderness, named for their dramatic, white-gray granitic peaks. Until my most recent trip to the Trinities, I had only been up Canyon Creek and the Stuart Fork trails, which are both in the central White Trinities, explaining why I had never witnessed (dun dun dun)<em>...the other Trinities</em>.

On the weekend before the 4th of July (technically not a long weekend, but pro tip: you can make any weekend a long weekend if you just take Monday off!), my roommate Cassie, our friend Katie and I hiked out of Swift Creek trailhead, at the east end of the wilderness boundary. Our plan was to hike west to Granite Lake, set up camp, and then spend the next day hiking up to Seven Up Pass and then returning to our camp at the lake. The trail follows the path of Swift Creek towards the heart of the Trinity Alps (the source of the creek) with some beautiful meadows and waterfall views along the way. As we climbed upwards and neared Granite Lake, a towering red ridge came into view to the north - our first sighting of the Red Trinities As the trail continued to climb, we could start to see gray mountains straight in front of us and on our left (i.e. west and south) - the White Trinities that are more “classic” Trinity Alps.

[caption id="attachment_402" align="alignnone" width="4032"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-402" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_2368.jpg" alt="IMG_2368" width="4032" height="3024" /> Red Trinities tower above us in the north[/caption]

<div>

[caption id="attachment_404" align="alignnone" width="4032"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-404" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_2466.jpg" alt="IMG_2466" width="4032" height="3024" /> And the White Trinities coming in hot to the south![/caption]

</div>
After 5 miles of hiking we reached our destination for the evening:, Granite Lake, a perfect glacial lake appropriately nestled underneath the gray granite ridge. Much to the chagrin of Cassie's aching feet, we then spent a good hour searching for The Best Possible Campsite. Finding The Best Possible Campsite is a super important thing for me - I love settling into a little nook of nature that feels homey and ideally has a great view of a body of water. After some circling, a creek crossing, and some wandering, we ended up setting up camp (aka throwing down our backpacks and laying out sleeping bags, summer backpacking is the best) at the top of a sweet little bump that gave us a great view of the lake, Granite Peak to the west, and the red ridge and Seven Up Peak to the north. The contrast between the two rock types was strikingly beautiful. We fell asleep under a blanket of endless shooting stars, gently contained by towering multi-colored mountains.

[caption id="attachment_384" align="alignnone" width="6000"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-384" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0428.jpg" alt="DSC_0428" width="6000" height="4000" /> A+ campsite[/caption]

<div>

[caption id="attachment_388" align="alignnone" width="6000"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-388" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0416.jpg" alt="DSC_0416" width="6000" height="4000" /> Where rock types collide![/caption]

</div>
The next morning we made our way north and west past Granite Lake up towards Seven Up Pass, basically hugging and then winding west up the red ridge. It was a short but sometimes steep hike up to the pass, and well worth it for the gorgeous views of the Four Lakes Loop basin. Once again, we faced the Red Trinities contrasted against the Whites, which continued to be stunning. At this point, I was regretting not having brought our packs up the pass, which would have let us do a loop hike and spend a solid half day hiking through the basin, but that’ll just have to be an adventure for another day.

[caption id="attachment_391" align="alignnone" width="6000"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-391" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0449.jpg" alt="DSC_0449" width="6000" height="4000" /> View from Seven Up Pass. White! Red! White![/caption]

I assume that by now you are wondering, “but why Katy? Why are there different kinds of rocks in the Trinity Alps?” The different colored rocks of the Trinity Alps has to do with the geologic history of the mountain range, and in fact of the entire Klamath Mountains, which happens to be fairly complex and fascinating. I found a book chapter about the natural history of the Klamaths, which had this to say:
<blockquote>"The region’s complex pattern of mountains and rivers creates a bewildering set of landscapes... Rocks laid in the distant past tell stories of ancient seas, of landmasses from throughout the world that have been added to North America, and of lofty mountain ranges that have worn down only to rise again. Pleistocene ice and now today’s events mold the area’s rivers and mountains. No wonder the area is confusing.”<em> - Northwest California, A Natural History (John Sawyer)</em></blockquote>
So! The bar for complexity is set high, but I will do my best to explain. This particular geologic story begins in the Mesozoic era, about 400 million years ago, when the California land mass was much smaller than it is today - the Klamath Mountains and Coast Ranges weren’t attached to the land at all. The rocks that make up the Klamath Mountains were once volcanic islands and other bits of the ancient ocean floor. The ocean floor isn’t static - it moves outward from spreading centers, and can collide with continents at what are known as convergent boundaries. About 400 million years ago, the ocean floor in the Pacific Ocean collided with the west coast of ancient North America, and because the rocks that make up the ocean floor are much heavier than the rocks that make up the continent, the ocean floor slid under continental North America, a process called subduction. As the ocean floor slid under the land, some of the seafloor (especially the volcanic islands) got scraped off the ocean plate and stuck onto the continent, which we call accretion. This happened 8 times over the course of the next ~300 million years. Ocean floor and volcanic rocks are heavy, and rich in iron and magnesium (a characteristic we describe as mafic). This is the basis for the red rocks found throughout the Klamath Mountains (including the Trinity Alps) and the coast ranges.

So Red Trinities? Check. What about the White Trinities? Where did that granite come from? As the ocean floor moved under the North American plate, its rocks heated and some melted, producing magma. This magma bubbled up into the continental crust, but some of it cooled before ever breaking the surface, basically a volcano that lost its steam. When magma cools slowly underground like this, it results in coarse grained rock called a pluton - pluton just describes any mass of rock that cooled and formed underground, a la the cooled magma chamber of a volcano. The White Trinities are made up of granodiorite plutons that formed from this process.

The diagram below does a pretty decent job at showing both the accretion process and the subsequent ocean floor melting/bubbling up/cooling that produces plutons. I stole it from a nifty little <a href="http://blogs.agu.org/georneys/2011/06/05/geology-word-of-the-week-a-is-for-accretionary-wedge/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">American Geophysical Union blog post</a> that describes subduction and accretion far better than I can.

<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-422" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/illustrations_convergent_boundary-e1500423756586.jpg" alt="illustrations_convergent_boundary" width="1000" height="630" />

The geology of the Klamaths becomes even more complicated due past glaciation as well as lots of metamorphic action caused by all of the pressure and stress of those eight accretions - all that pushing and scraping produced so much heat and pressure that rocks got squished and melted, changing both their texture and chemistry. That’s an explanation that I’ll shelf for now - but check out the reference at the end of this post if you’re interested in the metamorphic history of the mountain range. It is truly fascinating.

Because I have a serious armchair geology problem as well as a deep and undying obsession with CalTopo, when I got home from our backpacking trip I did the most reasonable thing to do, which was overlay our hiking route on a geologic map of the area and see if our views matched up with how the rocks were mapped. I assume this is a thing that everyone does either before or after hikes, and I’m not interested in hearing otherwise. On this map, our route is shown in red, and a few points (aka the start, camp spot, and the pass we hikes to) are marked with red X’s. The colors overlaid on the satellite image show what the different rocks are mapped as. The granodiorite (“white”) Trinities are shown in orange (I didn’t pick the colors) and the ultra-mafic (“red”) Trinities are shown in red. There’s also some yellow, which shows glacial till (rocks that got moved around by glaciers when the region was glaciated). The views on our hike match the map pretty darn well! On day one, we hiked west from the start point the the Best Campsite Ever. You can see the red, ultra-mafic ridge to our north as we hiked to the lake, and then the granitic area to the west that we could see from our campsite.

[caption id="attachment_410" align="alignnone" width="2006"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-410" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-3-57-33-pm.png" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-18 at 3.57.33 PM" width="2006" height="858" /> Geologic map for our hike in to Granite Lake![/caption]

On day two, we continued west past the lake to Seven Up Pass. If you imagine yourself standing on the pass looking westward over the basin, you can see the granite unit next to the ultra-mafic unit once again, giving that awesome contrast between the white and red Trinities.

[caption id="attachment_415" align="alignnone" width="2142"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-415" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-4-47-21-pm.png" alt="Screen Shot 2017-07-18 at 4.47.21 PM" width="2142" height="1194" /> Map of our view from Seven Up Pass (note that north is oriented to the right)[/caption]

[caption id="attachment_419" align="alignnone" width="6000"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-419" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0464.jpg" alt="DSC_0464" width="6000" height="4000" /> And oh how well the map matches our view! (Also how cute are we?!)[/caption]

Perhaps unsurprisingly, I really love doing this kind of thing. I think it’s super fun to learn a little bit about the history of an area, be it on a geologic time scale or a human time scale, especially when that information explains something that is cool, beautiful, or otherwise unique about that area. Knowing about the rocks that give rise to the epic beauty of the Trinities makes me feel more connected to these mountains that I already loved, which in turn makes me enjoy hiking there even more. This is part of why I love being a biogeochemist; working to understand a little bit more about the world around me gives even more meaning to the places that already fill me with awe. It’s fun to remember that although I don’t have to be constantly engaged in my research no matter where I go (in fact, it would be super unhealthy to do that), it’s always possible to learn a little but more about the places I love by taking a look at a map, pulling out a plant guide, or heck, looking at Wikipedia.

Also, I sometimes feel that as an earth scientist I’m supposed to have a decent understanding of plate tectonics and take it for granted that duh the continents travel around on these plates that sometimes smash into each other and sometimes one runs the other one over and one melt. However, every time I think about plate tectonics and the formation of mountains as we know them today, my mind is absolutely blown. Childish as it may be, I try my best to hold onto this sense of wonder and not become desensitized to just how cool our planet is. In a recent episode of This American Life, Ira Glass talks about magic tricks, and how sometimes understanding the underlying mechanics of a magic trick is way cooler than just watching the trick itself. I feel this way about the mountains; there is a certain magic that I feel within the mountains, and gaining an understanding of the processes that shaped and continue to shape these places deepens my sense of awe.

You can read about the geologic history of the Klamath Mountains <a href="https://content.ucpress.edu/pages/9691/9691.ch01.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>. And, you can download a KML file with a geologic map of your state (viewable in Google Earth) <a href="https://mrdata.usgs.gov/geology/state/">here</a>. Happy hiking!

<em>Major disclaimer: I am not a geologist. I may have made mistakes in this explanation/map interpretation/etc. As a scientist, facts matter to me - so if you find a mistake, please let me know so I can correct it!</em>]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>382</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-19 19:49:50</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-19 19:49:50</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="adventures"><![CDATA[adventures]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="backpacking"><![CDATA[backpacking]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="mountains"><![CDATA[mountains]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="places-and-spaces"><![CDATA[places and spaces]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="science"><![CDATA[science]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[7264403478]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:comment>
    <wp:comment_id>4</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Devin]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>devinrippner@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url/>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>108.85.89.19</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2017-07-21 06:05:47</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2017-07-21 06:05:47</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Wow, thanks for sharing, it was a great read. Im inspired to head up there to explore the trinity alps for myself.]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type/>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_notqueued</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1500617150</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>jabber_published</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1500617149</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>false</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:2:{s:4:"time";d:1500617149.892674922943115234375;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
  </wp:comment>
  <wp:comment>
    <wp:comment_id>7</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[johnsoares99]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>johnsoares99@yahoo.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url/>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>66.241.94.60</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2017-07-25 02:48:21</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2017-07-25 02:48:21</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I really appreciate the geology lesson! I’ve done that same hike several times, including going past Seven-Up Gap to the Four Lakes Loop. If you like “white” mountains, also check out the Russian Wilderness just to the north.]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type/>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>4618569</wp:comment_user_id>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>false</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1500950902.35783100128173828125;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:12:"johnsoares99";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_jobid</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>7460540042</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1500955361.40229701995849609375;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";s:4:"user";s:12:"johnsoares99";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_queued</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1500957825</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>jabber_published</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1500957825</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1500957825.930780887603759765625;s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:12:"katydynarski";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
  </wp:comment>
  <wp:comment>
    <wp:comment_id>8</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Susanne Twigiht-Alexander]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>ouzel@teleport.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url>http://www.susyouzel.com</wp:comment_author_url>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>67.171.196.94</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2017-07-25 03:16:05</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2017-07-25 03:16:05</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Really enjoyed this. I like the extra effort you put into your trips. If you haven't yet done so you might want to read David Rains Wallace's "The Klamath Knot".]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type/>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>false</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:2:{s:4:"time";d:1500952566.0329749584197998046875;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_jobid</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>7460564433</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_queued</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1500957894</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>jabber_published</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1500957894</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1500957894.6992309093475341796875;s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:12:"katydynarski";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
  </wp:comment>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DSC_0428</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/dsc_0428/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 04:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0428.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>384</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 04:51:40</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 04:51:40</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>dsc_0428</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0428.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DSC_0416</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/dsc_0416/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 05:01:13 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0416.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>388</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 05:01:13</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 05:01:13</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>dsc_0416</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0416.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DSC_0449</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/dsc_0449/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 05:02:55 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0449.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>391</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 05:02:55</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 05:02:55</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>dsc_0449</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0449.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Screen Shot 2017-07-16 at 10.42.29 PM</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/screen-shot-2017-07-16-at-10-42-29-pm/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 05:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/screen-shot-2017-07-16-at-10-42-29-pm.png</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>398</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 05:04:52</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 05:04:52</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>screen-shot-2017-07-16-at-10-42-29-pm</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/screen-shot-2017-07-16-at-10-42-29-pm.png</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IMG_2368</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/img_2368/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 21:55:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_2368.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>402</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 21:55:22</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 21:55:22</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>img_2368</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_2368.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IMG_2466</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/img_2466/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 21:56:13 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_2466.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>404</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 21:56:13</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 21:56:13</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>img_2466</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_2466.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Screen Shot 2017-07-18 at 3.57.33 PM</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-3-57-33-pm/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 23:24:43 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-3-57-33-pm.png</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>410</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 23:24:43</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 23:24:43</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-3-57-33-pm</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-3-57-33-pm.png</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Screen Shot 2017-07-18 at 4.47.21 PM</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-4-47-21-pm/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 23:51:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-4-47-21-pm.png</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>415</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 23:51:20</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 23:51:20</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-4-47-21-pm</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/screen-shot-2017-07-18-at-4-47-21-pm.png</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DSC_0464</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/dsc_0464/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 23:53:29 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0464.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>419</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-18 23:53:29</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-18 23:53:29</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>dsc_0464</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/dsc_0464.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>illustrations_convergent_boundary</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/07/19/green-mountains-red-mountains-and-white-mountains-oh-my/illustrations_convergent_boundary/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/illustrations_convergent_boundary.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>422</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-19 00:15:08</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-19 00:15:08</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>illustrations_convergent_boundary</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>382</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/illustrations_convergent_boundary-e1500423756586.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_wp_original_post_media</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[O:8:"stdClass":6:{s:4:"date";s:25:"2017-07-19T00:15:08+00:00";s:3:"URL";s:84:"https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/illustrations_convergent_boundary.jpg";s:4:"file";s:37:"illustrations_convergent_boundary.jpg";s:9:"extension";s:3:"jpg";s:9:"mime_type";s:10:"image/jpeg";s:4:"size";i:265936;}]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
</item>
<item>
  <title/>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/?p=520</link>
  <pubDate/>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=520</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img class=" size-thumbnail wp-image-522 aligncenter" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_0961-1-001.jpg?w=300" alt="IMG_0961 (1)-001" width="150" height="150" />
<p style="text-align:center;">I'm Katy Dynarski, a PhD student in Soils &amp; Biogeochemistry at UC Davis. I'm stoked on soils, the outdoors, female representation in science, adventure, science communication, conservation, and so much more.</p>]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>520</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-21 21:29:50</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name/>
  <wp:status>draft</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IMG_0961 (1)-001</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/?attachment_id=522</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 21:28:34 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_0961-1-001.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>522</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-07-21 21:28:34</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-21 21:28:34</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>img_0961-1-001</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>520</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_0961-1-001.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On academic culture, mental health, and why I didn't love "Lab Girl"</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2017/10/10/on-academic-culture-mental-health-and-why-i-didnt-love-lab-girl/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 23:35:42 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=536</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[My high school biology teacher sent me the widely-read scientific memoir Lab Girl by Hope Jahren about a year ago, saying it made him think of me. I enjoyed reading the story of another female biogeochemist (ours is not a story frequently told), and I hoped that the similarities between our areas of study were the reasons the book reminded Mr Roche of me. Because on a deeper level, this book bothered me. Jahren (beautifully and courageously) tells the story of her life as a scientist with manic depression, and though she does eventually get treatment, the book seems to treat her tendency to work all night, to be consumed by science, and to use her work as a way to define herself as a human being, with reverence. I remember being horrified after reading Lab Girl, knowing that I didn’t work that way and that I didn’t want to.

And yet the story of working in manic bursts and feeling intense pressure to publish papers, win research grants, or die trying, felt eerily familiar. These are common experiences in science, and habits that would be rightly recognized as signs of a mental health disorder outside of academia tend to be praised within academic culture. Personally, I have spent the past ~4 years of my life learning to recognize and manage an anxiety disorder that had not manifested until graduate school. I suspect that I have always been vulnerable to this condition and academia did not “cause” it, per se, but the fact remains that the demands of graduate school, and academia at large, preyed on and amplified my vulnerabilities and anxious tendencies until they became too apparent to not notice.

Anxiety for me is a gripping vortex of fear, a certainty that I am not enough and never will be, a pervasive sense of loneliness and longing, an inability to sleep, and a searing pain in my stomach that can prevent me from eating solid foods for days to weeks at a time (luckily my longest bout of this particular symptom was during a heat wave, which is a good time to subsist off of smoothies anyway). Anyone who says that mental health problems are all in your head should try occupying my body when I am experiencing an anxious peak. It is not an experience that I would recommend. My anxiety has ebbed and flowed throughout graduate school, and for years it would drive me to work harder and harder to stave off my feelings of inadequacy. I was tremendously productive during these periods, but I was not happy. About two years ago, I started to recognize that perhaps this wasn’t quite right and started to dabble in yoga and meditation to calm my mind, though changing my relationship to my work did not occur to me. I didn’t seek professional help until six months ago, and doing so scared the shit out of me. It was terrifying to learn that doubting myself, fixating on my inadequacies and flaws, and all of the other thought patterns that drove me to my greatest levels of productivity, were actually immensely unhealthy. Worse yet, the ONLY way for me to start feeling better was to do the very things that academia did not encourage me to do. I’ve been consciously working less, disentangling my concept of who I am as a person from my work, and learning how to shut my science brain off when I’m done working for the day. I hear a lot of academics say that their work always comes home with them, that they can never stop thinking about their work, and I think that we generally hail this as the pinnacle of being a true scientist. But after months of therapy, it doesn’t sound any different to me than the times my bran’s been caught in a holding pattern of articulating my own inadequacies. This is obviously not healthy, and I’ve been learning to cut those patterns off. So why do we praise people for this tendency within academic culture?

Maybe we love the idea of the tortured and brilliant soul, the scientist driven to madness by his own genius, the hero consumed by a scientific question who cannot focus on anything else. It’s a romantic concept for sure, but I’ve been there at times and it’s not much fun to live that way. Throughout my PhD, I’ve put in my time of letting my life be run by anxiety, by letting it increase my productivity at the expense of my health and sanity. I have watched myself and so many of my friends convince ourselves that we are succeeding, even as we were failing our own bodies and minds. I have privately wondered how long I could last working at the expense of my well-being, until enough conversations with friends and colleagues convinced me that this was something I should not have to do at all. I may not be literally Done With This, because I am a scientist and that’s what I want to do, and I’m not walking away from the academic system just yet. Figuratively, though, I am Done With This, if This is “allowing my job to exploit the anxiety disorder that I’m not even entirely sure I had before this job."

This summer, I took the academic equivalent of a vacation by spending three months working on a side project in another state. I didn’t take on extra work while I was there and I rode my mountain bike a lot and gave myself permission to spend my evenings cooking, crafting, and painting instead of working. I picked blackberries, drank tea, laughed a lot, looked at wildflowers, and spent as much time outside as I wanted. I felt good, grounded, and saner than I’ve felt in years. I also felt resurgences of anxiety plenty of times, but thanks to some space from my regular academic environment along with skills gained from months of therapy, yoga, and a meditation practice, I was able to sit with that anxiety and let it go, rather than use it to fuel a frenzy of productivity that would surely be praised by others but leave me drained. And you know what happened? I got my work done. I could have done more, could have probably written another chapter of my dissertation, but I didn’t, and the world didn’t end. So this narrative, that you have to work all hours to be worth your salt as a scientist, that exploiting your internal vulnerabilities in order to get more work done is something praiseworthy, can go to hell as far as I am concerned. I liked my summer of science and sanity, and I’m looking forward to many more months of both of those things.

I am an early-career scientist not yet finished with my PhD, and I know that we don’t have much room to bargain. There are too many of us and not enough faculty positions. Realistically, those jobs will go to those who have published the most, won the most grant money, and at the rate that I’ve been working, that’s not going to be me. That’s okay. I am smart, creative, a good problem solver, and a decent writer. I’ve had good working relationships with all of my advisors. My PhD was funded by a fellowship from the National Science Foundation, and I’ve been pretty successful at picking up research funding throughout my budding academic career. I work hard, but within reason now, and I will openly admit to loving my cat and my friends and my family more than I love my job. If these traits and accomplishments aren’t enough, if that last sentence puts me out of the running for my next position, so be it. This is, after all, just a job. But I’d like to stick around for a while and keep asking questions about the world around me (it’s a cool way to make a living), so here’s to hoping that as academics, we talk more openly about our work culture and shift towards something that’s healthier for everyone. In my heart I’m still a lab girl, I just can’t be Lab Girl.]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>536</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-10-10 23:35:42</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2017-10-10 23:35:42</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>on-academic-culture-mental-health-and-why-i-didnt-love-lab-girl</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="anxiety"><![CDATA[anxiety]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="grad-school"><![CDATA[grad school]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[10187568509]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:comment>
    <wp:comment_id>24</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Andy]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>andyzhang@ctemc.org</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url/>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>208.87.236.201</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2017-10-25 14:47:38</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2017-10-25 14:47:38</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Interesting! :D]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type/>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:2:{s:4:"time";d:1508947689.4793109893798828125;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_notqueued</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1508948014</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>false</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:2:{s:4:"time";d:1508942859.5140879154205322265625;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>jabber_published</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1508948014</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1508948014.9697339534759521484375;s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:12:"katydynarski";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
  </wp:comment>
  <wp:comment>
    <wp:comment_id>20</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Devin]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>devinrippner@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url/>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>108.85.89.19</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2017-10-10 23:44:32</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2017-10-10 23:44:32</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Thank you Katy, the feelings you express are eerily similar to my own. You are not alone in this; thank you for reminding me that i am not either.]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type/>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>jabber_published</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1507679074</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>false</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:2:{s:4:"time";d:1507679075.221314907073974609375;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_notqueued</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1507679075</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
  </wp:comment>
</item>
<item>
  <title/>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/?p=558</link>
  <pubDate/>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=558</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[It's almost Thanksgiving and I've been too full of happiness and excitement to focus on academic writing, so I figured I'd write a little post here. It's been a while.

Writing my]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>558</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2017-11-22 18:50:38</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name/>
  <wp:status>draft</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
</item>
<item>
  <title>"Acts of Sweaty Joy" published on Misadventures site!</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/03/06/acts-of-sweaty-joy-published-on-misadventures-site/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 00:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=565</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[This is not a real post, but one of my older posts was republished on the Misadventures mag website somewhat recently, and I wanted to share the news/link. Misadventures is one of my favorite publications written by and for outdoorsy women, and it's super exciting to have them highlight my work. Sharing my personal experiences with honesty and vulnerability is both challenging and terrifying, so it is always gratifying when the stories resonate with others.

<a href="https://misadventuresmag.com/acts-of-sweaty-joy/">Check it out here.</a>]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>565</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-03-06 00:58:20</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-03-06 00:58:20</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>acts-of-sweaty-joy-published-on-misadventures-site</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1520297902]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[15422311944]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:comment>
    <wp:comment_id>36</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Kathy Dynarski]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>dynarskik@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url/>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>209.85.220.177</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2018-03-06 16:38:38</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2018-03-06 16:38:38</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[😁 enjoyed your article just as much the second time! 

Sent from my iPhone 

&gt;]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type/>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:2:{s:4:"time";d:1520354318.842895030975341796875;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>false</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>comment_by_email_id</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>836739</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_notqueued</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1520356001</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>jabber_published</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1520355996</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1520355997.276856899261474609375;s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:12:"katydynarski";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1520356000.41094207763671875;s:5:"event";s:17:"status-unapproved";s:4:"user";s:12:"katydynarski";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1520356002.3768780231475830078125;s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:12:"katydynarski";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
  </wp:comment>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ode to the Peatland (The Places We Call Home)</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/04/20/ode-to-the-peatland-the-places-we-call-home/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 15:57:15 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=569</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[The first time that I truly felt like I was home, I was standing in the middle of a vast, green wetland approximately two thousand miles from my parent’s house. My feet, clad in fresh-from-the-hardware-store rubber boots up to my knees, sank into a soft carpet of moss that gave way with every step I took, the depressions filling with groundwater. This was not a place that should feel like home to a not-particularly-outdoorsy girl mostly raised in the New Jersey suburban sprawl, though truthfully, the generic sea of strip malls that I was raised within did not feel an authentic home. I grew up smack-dab in the middle of New Jersey, in a town that was technically fine but was also boxy, stifling, artificial, dead, and filled me with the suburban angst so stereotypical of my generation. In high school, I unironically embraced Holden Caulfield’s distaste for my hometown’s phoniness, but did nothing about it besides complain and walk around the mall. Dutifully, when it was time to go to college, I traded in my New Jersey suburb for a Pennsylvania suburb and studied biochemistry at a nice Catholic university. Biochemistry, I was told, was a good major to get into medical school with, and as a smart, curious kid who liked science, I was vaguely aware that I should go to medical school. It was only after my first year of school that I staged my first ever fit of rebellion, taking a stand against both my former job in a particularly uninspiring strip mall, and the medical school aspirations I realized did not belong to me, by taking a summer job as an ecology field research assistant. I was not certain what ecology really was, not even sure it meant to do field work (would there be a field?), I just knew that I’d be working for a lab doing some kind of science in Canada, where I had never been, and might possibly be outside, which seemed different.

And boy, was it different. After landing in Edmonton, Canada, we drove two hours north to a research station,  a few small buildings and a motley assortment of trailers surrounded by scrubby forests and a cattle farm. From there, we drove another three hours north, entirely on the same two-lane highway that appeared to mostly be utilized by logging trucks, to get to our first wetland field site, which to my untrained eyes looked big and empty of everything except for moss and water. I was on a team of ten people, and everyone but me seemed to know each other well. As we walked across the wetland on our first day of field work, their motions were fluid but relaxed as they picked their way adeptly past pools of water and hills of moss, while I lurched and reeled, every step threatening to overtop my uncomfortable boots. Field work, I gathered, consisted of walking around outside, pointing at various things, and talking about them, but I had no idea what everyone was pointing at and talking about. My unfamiliarity and ineptitude felt glaringly obvious, but nobody said anything, at least not to my face. And yet, the alien expanse of mossy wetland that I found myself within called to me, whispered really, welcome home, you’ve been away for so long, and though my boots didn’t fit and my phone no longer worked and I had packed way too much clothing but no towel and nothing in sight was familiar to me, I knew it to be true. The more time we spent walking, the more clear it became that the land we explored around on was complex, intricate, spontaneous, and full of the promise that there was something authentic and real beyond the concrete buildings that had formerly defined the boundaries of my existence. Life, which had always felt planned and stale and slightly underwhelming, suddenly felt like a grand adventure.

<img class="alignnone size-large wp-image-570" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_3022.jpg?w=2048" alt="IMG_3022" width="1024" height="768" />

When places call you home, the best thing that you can do is listen. So I stayed in that foreign but beautiful place. I learned to walk without filling my boots with water and to identify the surprisingly diverse array of tiny flowering plants battling for existence in their cold and wet world. It only took a few hours of causing everyone in the backseat to fear for their lives while I clumsily piloted our Ford F-150 around dirt roads for me to grasp the finer details of the ways in which driving a truck was different from driving my six-cylinder Pontiac. Halfway through the summer, I finally bought my first reusable water bottle. At some point, I even stopped putting on eyeliner before each day of field work. Eventually, that strange, vast expanse that was the peatland looked different to me. Abstraction gave way to details and I fell in love with the gentle hummocks and hollows of the moss underfoot, the delicate pink rosemary flowers that you had to kneel to distinguish, the stark bravery of lone jackpines dotting the landscape every hundred yards or so.

<img class="alignnone size-large wp-image-571" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_3009.jpg?w=2048" alt="IMG_3009" width="1024" height="768" />

This nagging feeling that the great northern peatland was the place that I belonged and had unknowingly been seeking throughout my discontented suburban upbringing manifested into an urgent need to understand how that place worked, to hold it in my hand and examine it with the lens that I understood best. For me, a biochemistry student with a new glimmer of purpose, that lens was chemistry. Summer after summer saw me tromping through Canadian bogs and fens with a backpack full of water samples and plant clippings. All would eventually be fed through one analytical machine or another, the expansive mysteries of a tangled web of life distilled into a series of numbers (how much carbon? how much nitrogen? where? when?). Knowing such numbers brought my fuzzy mental image of the ecosystem into focus and made concrete the chemical relationships between the mosses, the trees, the microscopic bacteria inhabiting the water. In this light, the reductionism of science became beautiful: it clarified and sharpened a complex and messy world so that I could better appreciate its intricacies. I spent the rest of college infatuated with peatland chemistry, immune to the bafflement of my friends who wondered why I studied moss, and moved to California after graduation for a PhD in biogeochemistry. Ostensibly the purpose of graduate school was to learn more chemistry, but deep down I was in pursuit of more ecosystems to peer at and try to comprehend, more ecosystems that would softly call me home.

I have found a hundred new homes since that first unexpected whisper, in mountains and forests and deserts. I’ve gone through uncountable pairs of boots, but I still own the same water bottle, and the world feels more real than it ever did from the inside of a strip mall. I study the chemistry of ecosystems but the science is almost coincidental to me; the point has always been to try and learn something about the places that tug at me so that I can translate their stories, and chemistry is the language that I speak most fluently. Through chemistry, I converse with wild landscapes, feel permanently entangled and entrenched in rolling hills, steep mountains, gnarled tree branches, the smell of fir needles, and rich organic soils teeming with life. Home, it turns out, has always been all around me.

<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-573" src="https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/2014-11-14-16-10-51-e1524239657913.jpg" alt="2014-11-14-16-10-51.jpg" width="2411" height="2692" />]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>569</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-04-20 15:57:15</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-04-20 15:57:15</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>ode-to-the-peatland-the-places-we-call-home</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="academia"><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="adventure"><![CDATA[adventure]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="adventures"><![CDATA[adventures]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="alberta"><![CDATA[alberta]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="biogeochemistry"><![CDATA[biogeochemistry]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="canada"><![CDATA[canada]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="ecology"><![CDATA[ecology]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="field-work"><![CDATA[field work]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="fieldwork"><![CDATA[fieldwork]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="grad-school"><![CDATA[grad school]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="home"><![CDATA[home]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="science"><![CDATA[science]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="wetland"><![CDATA[wetland]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1524239838]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[17004570871]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_thumbnail_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[570]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IMG_3022</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/04/20/ode-to-the-peatland-the-places-we-call-home/img_3022/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 15:38:44 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_3022.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>570</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-04-20 15:38:44</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-04-20 15:38:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>img_3022</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>569</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_3022.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IMG_3009</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/04/20/ode-to-the-peatland-the-places-we-call-home/img_3009/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 15:39:03 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_3009.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>571</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-04-20 15:39:03</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-04-20 15:39:03</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>img_3009</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>569</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_3009.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IMG_0156</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/04/20/ode-to-the-peatland-the-places-we-call-home/img_0156/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 15:52:50 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_0156.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>572</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-04-20 15:52:50</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-04-20 15:52:50</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>img_0156</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>569</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/img_0156.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2014-11-14 16.10.51</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/04/20/ode-to-the-peatland-the-places-we-call-home/2014-11-14-16-10-51/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 15:53:12 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/2014-11-14-16-10-51.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>573</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-04-20 15:53:12</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-04-20 15:53:12</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>2014-11-14-16-10-51</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>569</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/2014-11-14-16-10-51-e1524239657913.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_wp_original_post_media</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[O:8:"stdClass":6:{s:4:"date";s:25:"2018-04-20T15:53:12+00:00";s:3:"URL";s:70:"https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/2014-11-14-16-10-51.jpg";s:4:"file";s:23:"2014-11-14-16-10-51.jpg";s:9:"extension";s:3:"jpg";s:9:"mime_type";s:10:"image/jpeg";s:4:"size";i:3717569;}]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In Search of the Infinite Road Trip</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/06/05/in-search-of-an-infinite-road-trip/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 14:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=642</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[Like most other people, my roommate does not believe me when I say that I want to move into the back of my Honda CR-V and live immersed in nature once I finish my PhD in September. “You’re just trying to escape from stress,” she says, kindly but dismissively every time it comes up. “You’ll find a job if you look.”

I always say nothing when the conversation reaches this point, unsure how to explain that it’s not stress or escapism, just an increasing awareness that I do not fit into the academic environment, and the resulting discomfort. At my research university, I feel like a black sheep with my utter disregard for prestige and publications, my emotional view of science as the way I connect with the natural world. People with PhD’s from well-known universities go and get nice post-doctoral fellowships in big-name lab groups, or maybe with one of the national laboratories and then go on to be professors who slip references to their endless hours of work, recent publications, and multi-million dollar grants into every conversation, all of which feels painfully artificial to me. They certainly do not up and disappear into the wilderness to live a simple life in the back of a mid-size SUV, as I have so often fantasized about doing.

It’s not that I don’t want responsibilities. I love the work that I do as an ecosystem scientist and my side efforts as an advocate, educator, and writer. These callings all let me explore a genuine connection to the world around me, understand what it means to be a human, and consider my place in the vastness of the universe. For me, this work is about growing deep understandings, and even deeper roots.

So when I picture my own life in the back of my car, it isn’t because I’m looking for Chris McCandless-style life of escape - I’m seeking a life that puts that connection in the forefront of everything (yes, even before publications). I see my feet rooted in the places that mean the most to me, the mountains and forests and deserts that have sparked my curiosity and shaped my growth, getting to know them more intimately than I ever have before. I imagine immersing myself into these landscapes deeply enough for the bigger questions, the whys and the hows, to emerge and take shape from the molecules of the trees and the soil and the streams. I envision days brimming over with time to explore, to write, to lay my body down in the desert dust, look up at the infinite sky, and exist outside of myself. When I am in my office writing code for the third consecutive hour, wondering if my job means anything, I dream of a life that feels real and grounded and centered around the things I care most about. In this vision of a life that is driven by, rather than divorced from, my values, I carry out my work, this business of understanding, in the fullest, most engaged way.

It’s a romantic vision, one that I may never fulfill, but I think there’s value in recognizing what priorities our romantic notions are pulling us towards. The car is inconsequential, really; it’s about living a life, however winding or unusual, that honors my longings for simplicity, connectedness, and depth of experience. I went to a job interview this past weekend for a position that I think I’d really like, maybe even love, precisely because of its consistency with the values underlying this fantasy of mine, and I think that’s a pretty okay way to make decisions. For me, these cravings that seem to spill out of the deepest corners of my soul are worth paying attention to, worth shaping my life around, even if I don’t know what that looks like just yet.]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>642</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-06-05 14:51:40</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-06-05 14:51:40</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>in-search-of-an-infinite-road-trip</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>private</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="academia"><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="adventure"><![CDATA[adventure]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="adventures"><![CDATA[adventures]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="careers"><![CDATA[careers]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="ecology"><![CDATA[ecology]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="ecosystems"><![CDATA[ecosystems]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="grad-school"><![CDATA[grad school]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="road-trip"><![CDATA[road trip]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="science"><![CDATA[science]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="travel"><![CDATA[travel]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="vanlife"><![CDATA[vanlife]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_thumbnail_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[643]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1528210303]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[18635313014]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:comment>
    <wp:comment_id>39</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Ian Tully]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>ianmtully@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url/>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>99.203.92.88</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2018-06-07 19:04:51</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2018-06-07 19:04:51</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Having just graduated with my PhD in philosophy (and having just started a job I feel ambivalent about), I relate to this post so much. 

I wish I had known when I was 18 what my values and preferences would be now. The things I thought would make me happy and the kind of life I thought I wanted to lead them are not really the life I want to lead now. 

But in other ways I've always wanted the kind of life you describe. I wish I knew how to achieve it, and/or which kinds of careers would help me attain it or at least approximate it. How does one get to spend one's days in the open air, with freedom to create, to appreciate, to feel genuinely fulfilled? 

Anyway, thanks for the post. It gives articulate voice to exactly the same issues I'm currently struggling with and the same longings I've been feeling. Good luck on your quest. :)]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type/>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_result</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>false</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:2:{s:4:"time";d:1528398291.778222;s:5:"event";s:9:"check-ham";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>akismet_history</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>a:3:{s:4:"time";d:1528398325.033099;s:5:"event";s:15:"status-approved";s:4:"user";s:12:"katydynarski";}</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_queued</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1528398324</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>jabber_published</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>1528398324</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
    <wp:commentmeta>
      <wp:meta_key>email_notification_jobid</wp:meta_key>
      <wp:meta_value>18718020685</wp:meta_value>
    </wp:commentmeta>
  </wp:comment>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DSC_0036</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/06/05/in-search-of-an-infinite-road-trip/dsc_0036/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 14:50:26 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/06/dsc_0036.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>643</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-06-05 14:50:26</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-06-05 14:50:26</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>dsc_0036</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>642</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/06/dsc_0036.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Some Things, You Can Drive Away From</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/07/02/some-things-you-can-drive-away-from/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 16:08:41 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=658</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[Last July, I packed up my car full of every meaningful thing that I owned and drove north for eight hours to a different state. I had been awarded some funding months ago to support me in a research internship in northern Oregon, and the mandated change of scenery couldn’t have come at a better time. The months prior had been difficult, with personal upheaval and the alarming realization that although I was nearly done with my doctorate, I had very little that resembled a plan after that, spurring feelings of anxiety and not being enough that became consuming at times. I looked forward to the space, the distance from my everyday routine, in hopes that external changes would bring me the freedom that I could not quite grasp through my personal efforts. You can only go on so many long runs and leave yourself so many positive notes in your bathroom mirror before you start to feel a little silly and wonder why as an adult you aren’t better at handling your shit. Sometimes you just need to get out of town, and a fancy internship seemed like just as good an opportunity as any.

I marked the morning of my departure on my Google calendar in what felt like a cheerful purple shade. Amidst the endless slog of lab work and scientific writing that filled the days before I left, my feelings of anxiousness raging and quieting depending on the day, I silently repeated July 4th until it become a mantra for the day that things would feel different, if only because I’d be living somewhere else and slogging through different lab work and different scientific writing.

But when the time came to finally leave my driveway on that scorching Wednesday morning, I moved sluggishly, resistantly. I took my time loading my bikes onto the roof of my small SUV and said goodbye to my cat at least five times. It had been a year since I had been alone on the road for such a long stretch of time (2016, when I drove the 11 hours to and from the Sawtooth Mountains in Idaho by myself), and that was before I had had to spend months coaxing myself out of a deep well of fear and self-deprecation. Being alone, on the road and then in a new state after that, seemed like a good idea right up until the moment where I needed to buckle my seatbelt and start the ignition, at which point it seemed like a doomed enterprise. I worried for a brief moment that I would make it four hours or four weeks into my solo journey and realize that the change I had been looking forward to for so long was not helping me at all, and I would be trapped with myself and completely out of ideas. Then I took another breath, turned the key, and the V4 engine of my sensible Honda hummed to life, ready for anything that didn’t involve particularly high speeds or steep hills. I gratefully acknowledged the non-newness of my car, the satisfaction of turning a key, rather than pushing a button, to start off a journey. Maybe this would work, after all.

As I pulled out of the driveway, and eventually onto the freeway, the pressure on my chest, the one that had been there for so long that I had almost forgotten about it, loosened its hold just enough to remind me of its existence and non-normalcy. I took another, deeper, breath. During the months of caging panic, I had forgotten that I had the power to say no, to acknowledge and then figuratively walk away from the things that diminished me. Driving was a literal way to walk (well, drive) away, my bikes on the roof of my car reminding me that I could go anywhere if I gave myself permission and remembered to put air in my tires.

Driving away from home did not change my life (spoiler alert), but it did change my perspective. It gave me space and time to sit with quietly with myself, left with no choice but to accept myself because there was nothing and nobody else around. It was an opportunity to take stock of my own simple needs and then provide for them. When I needed a story, I turned on a podcast. When I needed to scream, I turned up the music. When I needed to stop at dingy gas stations to buy iced tea and eat Chex Mix, I did just that. It was a chance to be everywhere, nowhere, and just there all at the same time. I could visualize where I was going, where I was in that moment, and where I had been in the most visceral of ways. As I-5 bent west around Mount Shasta, I took comfort in my smallness compared to the behemoth volcano. Though it dominated the horizon for a full hour of my drive, it quickly disappeared from view as I climbed up the Siskiyou Crest and then down towards Ashland, and all of a sudden, I was in a different, greener place.]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>658</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-07-02 16:08:41</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-07-02 16:08:41</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>some-things-you-can-drive-away-from</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="academia"><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="adventures"><![CDATA[adventures]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="anxiety"><![CDATA[anxiety]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="grad-school"><![CDATA[grad school]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="road-trips"><![CDATA[road trips]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="science"><![CDATA[science]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="solo-travel"><![CDATA[solo travel]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="travel"><![CDATA[travel]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1530547724]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_thumbnail_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[660]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[19588654037]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DSC_0243</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/07/02/some-things-you-can-drive-away-from/dsc_0243/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 16:04:36 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/07/dsc_0243.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>659</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-07-02 16:04:36</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-07-02 16:04:36</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>dsc_0243</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>658</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/07/dsc_0243.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DSC_0243_01</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/07/02/some-things-you-can-drive-away-from/dsc_0243_01/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 16:07:58 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/07/dsc_0243_01.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>660</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-07-02 16:07:58</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-07-02 16:07:58</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>dsc_0243_01</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>658</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/07/dsc_0243_01.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Love Note to the Sonoma Coast</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/08/28/love-note-to-the-sonoma-coast/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 22:57:54 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=696</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[We stepped through the gate at the end of the road and onto a dirt path, lurching and uneven from years of being trodden by cows. The fog hung low and heavy, which on another day might have struck me as gloomy. Today, it was a welcome change from the smoky haze that the wildfires in the north had brought to my Central Valley town for the past few weeks, and the blazing sun that peeked out whenever the smoke subsided. I’ve always thought myself a mountain person, destined to settle in a valley surrounded by jagged peaks, but as we picked our way down and around the bluff, not talking or thinking about anything in particular, I thought that this lonely and rugged coastline wouldn’t be half bad.

I spend a lot of time writing, thinking, and talking about cultivating presence, but truth be told, I hadn’t felt very present in a long while. My summer calendar had been daunting and full of deadlines. On rare days off, I frantically packed in as much as activity possible. I’m sure there is something to be said for working hard and playing harder, but it wasn’t doing me much good. All I felt was too busy, disconnected, worried that my 27th year of existence would pass me by and I’d wake up from a daze, not sure what had happened or what it all meant. I momentarily forgot about that paradox while eating a hodgepodge picnic lunch in the dunes, enjoying the feeling of cool, salty air on my dry valley skin, surrounded by the kind of friends with whom I’ve never had to say much to feel understood.

Later, picking my way around the rocky shore, in search of tide pools and sea life, I shattered my budding presence with awareness of its existence. Trying to be where your feet are is like trying to fall asleep late at night - once you realize you are almost there, you ruin it. I thought about how I’d write about this day, and bitterly wondered if, in my quest to capture moments of love and joy and connection with words or through my camera lens, that I would reduce them all to fodder for a story or a caption. Does it cheapen my experiences by trying to record them in my mind once I realized they are happening? Does trying to write about connection doom me to forever be a third party, unable to fully experience my own life without the lens of description?

After an hour of spotting crabs scurrying from crack to crack and anemones swaying with mesmerizing regularity, we scrambled to the top of a towering boulder at the water's edge, enormous sea stars clinging to the slick wave-battered rocks below us. We watched the waves envelope, then reveal them, for what felt like hours but was probably only minutes. We never decided that it was time to turn around, but one by one everyone picked their way off the rock and headed back toward the dunes with careful steps. We made our way back up the bluff with the same lazy, rolling conversations that had brought us down it earlier that day, our words evaporating and then condensing into the clouds that still hung low around us. For now, my inner monologue quieted, my thoughts and body all a part of the grayness that swallowed me, dripping fingers of fog grazing the sea cliffs.]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>696</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-08-28 22:57:54</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-08-28 22:57:54</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>love-note-to-the-sonoma-coast</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="adventures"><![CDATA[adventures]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="places-and-spaces"><![CDATA[places and spaces]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1535497078]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_thumbnail_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[698]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[21561945297]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IMG_5851</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/08/28/love-note-to-the-sonoma-coast/img_5851/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 22:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/img_5851.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>697</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-08-28 22:55:59</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-08-28 22:55:59</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>img_5851</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>696</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/img_5851.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IMG_5851 2</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/08/28/love-note-to-the-sonoma-coast/img_5851-2/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 22:57:24 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/img_5851-2.jpg</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>698</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-08-28 22:57:24</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-08-28 22:57:24</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>img_5851-2</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>696</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <wp:attachment_url>https://biogeokaty.files.wordpress.com/2018/08/img_5851-2.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In the Era of Smoke and Night Shifts</title>
  <link>http://biogeokaty.com/2018/11/27/in-the-era-of-smoke-and-night-shifts/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2018 16:22:37 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>katydynarski</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://biogeokaty.com/?p=715</guid>
  <description/>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[It’s late November, and it should be raining, but it isn’t. Fire rages in the north, coloring the sky an ominous charcoal that would tell us that the earth is more powerful than human beings and our limitless hubris, if anyone were listening. The air tastes like a groggy morning after too many cigarettes, minus the memory of the nicotine rush. Soon we are told that it isn’t safe to go outside, for now. People in town scramble to buy breathing masks before they run out. I am out of town for a conference when things get really bad and miss out on my window to snag a mask. When I return, the university campus has closed due to the air quality, or lack thereof. First one day, then two, then the whole week. Email after frenzied email promises that the administration is doing everything it can to open campus up soon. A vague mention of not losing momentum is made. I try to imagine what the university might be doing to put out a 85,000 acre fire a hundred miles away, what they are doing to clean the air in our hazy valley town, what they could possibly do to reverse the effects of a century of burning fossil fuels. I come up with nothing.

So I stay inside, grateful that with my teaching duties temporarily lifted, I am free to work from the relative safety of my house. I burn candles to stave off the heavy scent of burning homes that lingers outside my window. I try to keep my cat inside, to no avail. In what passes for consolation, I question if my thin walls and single-pane windows are enough to protect our lungs anyway, and blink back unexpected tears when I remember how many people have lost so much more than their air quality. Nobody says the words "climate refugees" on the news, but here we are. I think about buying an air purifier, but they sound expensive, so I will join my human kin and try to gild over my demons rather than uproot them. Eucalyptus oil is powerful stuff, you know.

I try to work normal days despite all the upheaval, and come home at 10 pm after an evening meeting to a silent house. Nighttime has a strange ephemerality to it now, the smoke scattering the streetlights, making it never feel completely dark. Upstairs in the eery stillness, my partner and my cat are fast asleep, and I crawl into bed with them, grateful to still have our tiny family, fragile as the world may seem these days. We are warm and whole together for an entire hour, until an alarm clock shatters the tranquility and Erik wakes up for work. I stumble to the bathroom where he is getting dressed, kiss him goodbye and put on my pajamas, and then go back to sleep a few degrees colder than before. He works the night shift as an EMT in a casino that doesn’t care about human health so much as protecting its own bottom line. He is expected to exist, but not much else, for fear that the casino might be liable if he provides medical advice in his capacity as a medical professional. I wake up the next morning shivering with my cat pressed close to my body, bitterly wondering why a casino needs to be open for 24 hours a day anyway, why my gentle partner has been reduced to disposable protection against lawsuits, instead of providing medical care like he has worked so hard to be able to do.

I make coffee while my cat chirps for her breakfast, drink it while I write at my desk. I read a story about workers suffering tragic miscarriages while working at Amazon warehouses and worry that my sleep-deprived, forced-nocturnal partner will die in a car crash on his way home from work. Erik returns home, crash-free, a little after 9 and gets back into bed, falling into a restless slumber while my keyboard clicks. What with at least one of us being asleep at almost all hours of the day, I am never sure what time it is anymore, and it’s just as well, since the sky remains a bland, timeless gray, and we still can’t go outside. More and more, I wonder if the apocalypse is really here, this time. I am not sure if people know the apocalypse is happening while it’s happening, or if that’s just something you know in retrospect. Over and over, I question why we keep insisting on burning carbon to the benefit of nobody, why we pretend that fires getting worse and worse each year are a coincidence or somehow the result of this generation’s poor forest management. I mourn the fact that Erik’s job treats him and every other employee like an object and haphazardly assigns night shifts whenever it is convenient, without regard for the disruption and the health risk. The fires, the casino, the warehouses, it all feels the same. We wring people and the planet for all that they are worth, and here we are, unable to venture outside without breathing masks on but still demanding two-day shipping on air purifiers, while our country pulls out of the climate agreement and insists that there is no problem. I am not even certain what I should be grieving for anymore.

I type on in the dim morning light, searching for words, hoping for rain. When it finally comes, it comes in sheets, and desiccated fall leaves clog the storm drains, flooding the downtown streets.
]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id>715</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date>2018-11-27 16:22:37</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt>2018-11-27 16:22:37</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name>in-the-era-of-smoke-and-night-shifts</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status>publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password/>
  <wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="climate-change"><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="climate-refugees"><![CDATA[climate refugees]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="essays"><![CDATA[essays]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="fire"><![CDATA[fire]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="writing"><![CDATA[writing]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[24707586227]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1543335767]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta>
    <wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
